dr. ir. Roland M. van Rijswijk-Deij

University of Twente Faculty EEMCS (room ZI-5098) Drienerlolaan 5 NL-7522 NB Enschede The Netherlands

r.m.vanrijswijk@utwente.nl

♦ https://rijswijk.github.io

https://www.linkedin.com/in/rolandvanrijswijk

EDUCATION

02/2014 – 06/2017 Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science (cum laude)

University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands

09/1995 – 08/2001 Master of Science in Computer Science

University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

11/2018 – present NLnet Labs, Amsterdam, The Netherlands

Principal Scientist

Researching core Internet protocols (DNS, BGP, IP, ...)

09/2008 – 10/2018 SURFnet, Utrecht, The Netherlands

R&D Project Manager and Researcher

DNS, DNSSEC, Network Security, Network Measurements

11/2006 – 08/2008 InTraffic, Nieuwegein, The Netherlands

Lead Software Designer

Control Software for Railway and Public Transport Infrastructure

10/2002 – 11/2006 AET Europe, Arnhem, The Netherlands

Senior Software Engineer

Cryptographic Middleware and Embedded Software for Smart Cards

01/2001 – 10/2002 Royal Philips Electronics, Eindhoven, The Netherlands

Software and Test Engineer

09/2000 – 12/2000 British Telecommunications (BT) R&D, Ipswich, United Kingdom

Industrial Traineeship

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

11/2017 – present University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands

Assistant Professor (part-time)

In the Design and Analysis of Communication Systems Group, Faculty of Electrical Engineering, Maths and Computer Science

07/2017 – 10/2017 University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands

Guest Researcher

02/2014 – 06/2017 University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands

Ph.D. Candidate

02/2016 - 03/2016 CAIDA, University of California at San Diego, United States

Visiting Researcher

02/2013 – 02/2014 Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands

Ph.D. Candidate

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS (FULL LIST SEE HTTPS://RIJSWIJK.GITHUB.IO/)

- [1] T. Chung, R. van Rijswijk-Deij, B. Chandrasekaran, D. Choffnes, D. Levin, B.M. Maggs, A. Mislove and C. Wilson. *A Longitudinal, End-to-End View of the DNSSEC Ecosystem*. In Proceedings of the 26th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security '17). Vancouver, BC, Canada: USENIX Association. (*Acceptance Rate: 16.3%*)
- [2] R. van Rijswijk-Deij, K. Hageman, A. Sperotto, and A. Pras. *The Performance Impact of Elliptic Curve Cryptography on DNSSEC Validation*. IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, vol. 25, no. 2, 2017. (*Impact Factor 2016/2017: 3.376*)
- [3] R. van Rijswijk-Deij, M. Jonker, A. Sperotto, and A. Pras. A High-Performance, Scalable Infrastructure for Large-Scale Active DNS Measurements. IEEE Journal of Selected Areas in Communications, vol. 34, no. 7, pp. 1877–1888, 2016. (Impact Factor 2016/2017: 8.085)
- [4] R. van Rijswijk-Deij, A. Sperotto, and A. Pras. *DNSSEC and Its Potential for DDoS Attacks*. In Proceedings of ACM IMC 2014, 2014. (Acceptance Rate: 22.9%)
- [5] G. van den Broek, R. van Rijswijk-Deij, A. Sperotto, and A. Pras. DNSSEC Meets Real World: Dealing with Unreachability Caused by Fragmentation. IEEE Communications Magazine, vol. 52, no. April, pp. 154–160, 2014. (Impact Factor 2014: 4.007)

Awards

2019 PAM Best Dataset Award

Paper: "A First Look at QNAME Minimization in the Domain Name System" presented at Passive and Active Measurements, March 27-29, 2019, Puerto Varas, Chile

IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP)

Paper: "Understanding the Role of Registrars in DNSSEC Deployment" to be presented at IETF 105, July 20-26, 2019, Montréal, Canada

2018 IFIP/IEEE NOMS Best Paper Award

Paper: "Melting the Snow: Using Active DNS Measurements to Detect Snowshoe Spam Domains" presented at IFIP/IEEE NOMS, April 23-27, 2018, Taipei, Taiwan

TMA Best Open Dataset Award

Paper: "Passive Observations of a Large DNS Service: 2.5 Years in the Life of Google" presented at TMA 2018, June 25-29, 2018, Vienna, Austria

2017 USENIX Security Distinguished Paper Award

Paper: "A Longitudinal, End-to-End View of the DNSSEC Ecosystem" [1] presented at the 26th USENIX Security Symposium, August 16-18, 2017, Vancouver, BC, Canada

IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP)

Paper: "The Performance Impact of Elliptic Curve Cryptography on DNSSEC Validation" [2] presented at IETF 100 in Singapore, November 2017

2015 IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP)

Paper: "DNSSEC and Its Potential for DDoS Attacks" [4] presented at IETF 94 in Yokohama, Japan, November 2015

2014 ACM SIGCOMM IMC Community Contribution Award

Paper: "DNSSEC and Its Potential for DDoS Attacks" [4] presented at ACM SIGCOMM IMC 2014, Vancouver, BC, Canada, November 2014

SHORT BIOGRAPHY

Roland van Rijswijk-Deij was born in Arnhem, The Netherlands, on March 17th, 1977. He holds an M.Sc. degree in Computer Science from the University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands (2001). Roland received a *cum laude* Ph.D. degree from the University of Twente in June 2017, for his thesis entitled "Improving DNS Security: a Measurement-Based Approach". Roland has a background in embedded systems, applied cryptography and networking. He previously worked for British Telecom (2000, traineeship), Royal Philips Electronics (2001-2002), AET Europe (2002-2006), InTraffic (2006-2008) and SURFnet (2008-2018).

Since 2018, Roland is principal scientist at NLnet Labs, a not-for-profit foundation that performs research on, and develops open source software for, the core protocols of the Internet. Past innovation projects initiated by Roland have focused on DNS, DNSSEC, detecting and mitigating DDoS attacks, IPv6 and many other topics. Roland regularly presents his work in international networking venues, such as TNC, Internet2 conferences, IETF meetings, ICANN meetings, RIPE meetings and NANOG.

Next to his work at NLnet Labs, Roland is assistant professor computer network security in the Design and Analysis of Communication Systems group at the University of Twente.